This is the Dedication Chapter
from The Guide to Bodhisattva's Way of Life
by Master Shantideva.
Thus have I completed writing
A Guide to the Bodhisattva's Way of Life
and I pray
that by this goodness every living being
may take up this way of life.
By the power of this good deed too may any
single living creature in sickness or in
pain, of body or mind, in any corner of
this universe, be thrown into a sea of
bliss.
And for as long as they may wander
in the circle of suffering life, may they
never lose this bliss. May every one of
them one day reach the bliss beyond all
other, and stay there
never-ending.
I don't know how many
realms of hell there are hidden in our
world; but by this power may every person
trapped in one instead find joy in the
joy of the Heaven of Joy.
May those who
freeze in the cold of hell be covered in warmth.
May infinite showers of gentle
rain fall from vast bodhisattva clouds to
cool the searing pain of those who live
there in fire. May the forest of falling
leaves of knives turn for those who
live there into a pleasure grove of
shady bowers. May the daggers of the
trunks of the trees of Shalmali
sprout as the Wish-Giving Tree instead.
May the caverns of hell suddenly echo
forth
with the soft sweet song of the dove and
nightingale, ruby-throated sparrow,
graceful swans, birds of every kind, drawn
to the gentle waters that spring up
instantly there, covered with lotuses
whose delicate fragrance fills the air.
May the heaps of burning embers of fire
become piles of precious jewels, and the
red-hot glowing
iron floor the ground of a new world,
sparkling in crystal light. May the
mountains that slam together, crushing
the crowds of helpless people between
them, turn to the palace temples of
heaven, filled with bliss-filled Buddhas.
In the moment that I speak may the great
rain of putrid filth, and stones of
solid fire, knives, and spears, turn
into a soft steady shower of fragrant
flower petals. And in the hells of anger,
where people snatch up rocks and sticks
to gash one another open, may they instead
gather up armfuls armfuls of petals,
laughing, tossing over each other. I send
the awesome power of the good deed that
I've done as well to all those trapped
within the river that cannot be crossed,
wrapped within the hell-flame there, with
all the skin and flesh ripped away from
their bodies, the bones jutting out in
the glistening white of freshly fallen
snow; may this power grow their bodies
back, in the form of divine Angels. And
then may the beings in hell take pause,
and wonder suddenly to themselves, "Why
now do the henchmen of the Lord of Death
and his vicious ravens, and the birds of
prey, why did they turn and run from us?
What glorious power has turned the night
of hell to golden day, and smothered us
within this happiness, this strength, this
bliss? Who could have such power?" And may
they raise their eyes and see the blue
of sky, and seated in it The One Who
Holds the Diamond in Their Hand. And then
may joy spread in their hearts, so
powerful that it tears away every wrong
they ever did, and so then they can rise
and fly--fly away with this Buddha. May
a rain of lovely flower petals mixed with
cool and perfumed water descend in a
song and extinguish the flames of the
fires that burn in hell.
May the beings who lived there look upon
this sight, and suddenly be overcome by
happiness. And then may they think to
themselves, "Who could have done this
thing?" And may they turn and see before
them The One who Holds the Lotus in
Their Hand. And then may the hell beings
hear a voice that calls to them and says:
"Come my friends, so far away, cast away
your fears now, and come be at my side;
Come to the one whose power has stripped
away your agony and thrown you into joy."
And when they lay their eyes on this one,
on Gentle Voice himself or herself, may
every miserable creature there burst
forth in a song, a song that roars
throughout the hells, a song that sings: "You
are the Bodhisattva who protects every
single living being, overcome by your
love for them; you are the youth divine,
with your flowing locks, body blazing in
light; how could it be that you have come
to us, and smashed the terrors here? Are
you not the one to whom a thousand gods
would run, to touch the tips of their
crowns at your lotus feet? The one whose
eyes glisten in tears of compassion for
us? The one on whom a constant shower
of petals falls? See him or her now--
surrounded by palaces filled with crowds
of celestial youths
singing out their praises!" Oh thus may
it come to pass, through the power of the
goodness that I have done: every
suffering being in hell, wrapped now deep in
happiness, standing staring up at clouds
as they gather overhead, and the reality
of the bodhisattvas--the one whose name
is Sheer Excellence and all the rest--
uncovered fully in the light, sending
down upon them showers of the rain that
brings them bliss, cool soft rain, rain of
finest fragrance. And by this power may
every being who lives in the animal
realm be freed from the terror of
feeding off each other. May those who
live as craving spirits enjoy a life of
peace and plenty,
like humans of the isle of Haunting
Voice. May a stream of milk descend from
the hand of the Lord of Power, the
Realized One, the One Who Looks with
Loving Eyes, and may it fill the spirits
who crave, washing them too in a gentle
bath, leaving them cool and refreshed.
And  by this power made the blind open
their eyes and see the beauty; may the
deaf hear the song of sound. May every
woman with child give birth as Maya, the
Buddha's angel mother, did him--without a
hint of pain. May those without
sufficient clothing be suddenly clothed;
may the hungry be instantly filled with
food. May those who suffer now from
thirst drink fine fresh water and other
delicious beverages. May every poor
person there is find all the money they
need; may those who grieve be comforted.
May those who've lost hope
find hope anew, and security that will
never leave them. May every single being
who is sick within this entire universe
be suddenly, totally, cured. May every kind
of disease ever known to living kind
vanish now, forever.
May all those in any kind of fear be
suddenly freed from it. May those
imprisoned be released. May those
downtrodden come to power, all of us
living then as family, in harmony with
each other. May all of those who are on
the road, to anywhere at all, be safe and
comfortable, wherever they are now. And
may they without the slightest trouble
find at the end of their journey the
thing they left their home to find. May
all those who've left dry land to travel
in boats or ships accomplish all they
set out to do. May they cross the dangers
of the waters and then return safe to
their homes, and the arms of friends and
family. May those who travel a barren
waste, or mistake their way, who
wander lost, suddenly come upon new
companions and find their way easily,
free of fatigue, without the slightest
danger of things like thieves or wild
beasts. May holy angels come and protect
all those who live in fear, with nowhere
to go, no path to follow:
small children, the elderly, those with no
one to help them; those who cannot sleep,
those who are troubled, and the insane. May
they spend every life they still have to
live free of every obstacle to a
spiritual life: may they find firm
feelings of faith, and wisdom, and a
perfect capacity for love; may their
physical needs be filled,
may they lead good lives. May they have
all they need to live, forever,
without a moment's pause, as if they
possessed the treasure of the magic sky.
May they live together without ever
quarreling, without ever hurting each
other, enjoying instead the freedom to
live as they choose to. May every person
who is small or shy, who has no
confidence, become strong and full of
grace. May those who lived a life of need
and suffered from it physically
recover in resplendent health. May all
those who live in a place in society where
they are not treated right transform
forever to a position ideal. May those
who are looked down upon be raised up
high, and their arrogant friends be
tumbled to the ground. And by this
goodness I have done may every single
suffering being give up every single
harmful thought or word or deed; taking
up always in its stead thoughts and words
and deeds of virtue. May these beings
never cease to strive to reach the
ultimate goal, for others; and may their
hearts be swept away by the stream of
loving conduct. May they abandon every
sort of dark behavior, remaining in the
care of every Holy Being. May every
living soul enjoy a life immeasurably
long, living thus forever in a state of
constant bliss, so that even the very
word "death" is never heard spoken again.
May all the places that exist, in every
world there is, turn instantly into
gardens of elegant design, filled with
trees that grant your every wish. And may
the Enlightened Ones, along with their
daughters and their sons, walk amidst the
trees, singing out the sweet song of the
Dharma. And in each one of these places
may the very foundation the earth itself,
be transformed, from sharp stones and the
like, into the heavenly ground of lapis
lazuli--as smooth as the palm of your
hand, and soft to walk upon.
And like a precious jewel adorning this
same ground, may all the secret worlds
that exist and all the goodness in them
abide atop these newfound lands, crowded
with Warrior Angels. And too, may all
who live and breathe hear the song of
birds, the wind in the trees, the light of
the sun, and the sky itself, singing aloud
to them an endless rhapsody of holy
teachings. And wherever they go may they
always meet the Enlightened Ones, and
their children who strive for
enlightenment. May they honor these Lamas--
the highest of beings--with endless
showers of offerings. May the lords of
the sky send down the rains on time, so
to bring forth plentiful harvests. May
all existing governments make their
decisions based on the teachings, and
thus made the whole world prosper. May
every medicine come to have the power to
cure; may the secret words fulfill all
hopes. May the minds of gods and spirits
of sickness alike be overcome with
thoughts of compassion. May no single
living being ever again feel a single
pain. May they never again feel afraid,
never again be hurt by another, never
again be unhappy. May places of spiritual
learning thrive, filled with people
reading sacred books, and singing them
out loud as well. May communities of
spiritual practitioners live always in
harmony, and may they achieve the high
goals for which they live together. May
all those who have ever taken the vows
of a monk come to master the arts of
solitude, throwing off every kind of
distraction, gradually refining their
minds, learning perfect meditation. May
nuns forever find support for their
physical needs, and live lives free of
conflict or any outside threat.
May every person who's ever become
ordained conduct themselves perfectly in
their moral code. And may any of those
who may have ever broken this code
regret what they've done, and always
work to clean the karma.
May they then return to a higher birth,
and in their new life never see their
spiritual discipline fail again. May
every sage who lives in this world find
the honor due to them, and always be
offered the food and other needs they
request. May they always take care that
their hearts are pure, and may they earn
a good name that spreads throughout the
entire world. May none of these people
ever again undergo the pain of the lower
realms; in strength beyond the strength
of gods
may they quickly win the state of a
fully Enlightened One without the
slightest hardship. May every suffering
being there is make offerings over and
over again to every Enlightened Being
there is. And may the Enlightened Ones
enjoy forever what we have offered them,
in infinite waves of bliss. May every
plan there is in the heart of every
bodhisattva to help every living being come
true. May everyone get every single thing
that the Enlightened Ones who shelter us
have in mind for us to get. May those who
follow the lower paths of self-made
awakened ones, and listeners, attain the
happiness they seek. And may we, through
the kindness of Gentle Voice, remember in
life after life who we are and what we
practice, rejecting the worldly way of
life again and again, until the day we
reach the level called Intense Joy. May
we gain the mystic ability to live off
even the poorest of food, growing ever
more strong and healthy. In all our lives
may we win the wealth of learning to
live in solitude with nothing more than
the barest needs. And when anyone ever
longs to see him,
or ask him even the slightest question,
may the shroud which covers their eyes be
torn away, so that the High Protector,
Lord Gentle Voice Himself, instantly
appears.
We are working to achieve the
goals of all the living beings there are
in every corner of this universe;
and so
by this power may we learn to do every
single one of the things that Gentle
Voice is able to do. And may we decide
that we will stay to work to clear away
the pain of every living being there is
until the last day of this universe;
until the very last suffering creature
is changed.
May every single pain that is
coming to any single being there is
ripen now upon me instead.
May the great community of bodhisattvas
go forth and spread throughout through
all the world, to work for the happiness
of all.
The teachings of the Enlightened
Ones are the one medicine that can cure
the great sickness of living kind. They
are the one ultimate source of every
form of happiness. And so by this power
may the teachings remain long upon this
planet, with all the support they require,
and all the respect they deserve.
And
lastly do I bow myself down to the one
with a Gentle Voice, the One who has been
kind enough to teach me the ways of
virtue;
thus last do I bow myself down to the
One who was kind enough to raise me up
from childhood: I bow to You, my Spiritual
Guide.